The process that I am going to tell you will be
valid on all types of insurance like health
insurance, life insurance, car
insurance, cyber security, household
insurance, everything will be valid on all types of insurance,
so the entire process will be the same,
listen, so first of all, after the claim is rejected,
you have to get a
rejection letter from the company,
how will you get a rejection letter from the company, generally when your claim
is rejected, it will automatically come to your registered
email ID, in case it does not come, then
call customer care, email customer care,
where will you get the email ID,
go to the company's website, from there you will get the
email ID, you will also get the customer care phone
number, they will give it, in case they do
not give it even then, then the email ID of the grievance cell will be
given on the grievance cell,
email there on grievance redressal, they will
give the rejection letter in kindly provided,
so after getting the rejection letter,
then you have to create a new fresh email,
which is the next step, you have to email the grievance cell, you have to
create a new fresh email, it will be
written on it, kindly re  Do
write the keyword consider, reconsider, kindly reconsider the claim
and policy number in the subject line
and write three to four lines below it, kindly
reconsider my claim, I have
fully cooperated with the company
during the process of the claim and I
think they should this claim should get passed, kindly
reconsider the claim and approve my claim as soon as possible, write
three to four
lines like this,
people keep thinking about it more, they don't know
what to write and what not to write, it is simple,
writing three to four lines will get the job done, now there are
two ways to send a grievance retail mail,
one is you can do it directly by visiting the company's website, the
second way is by
complaining on IIDA, how does it happen on IIDA,
IIDA itself does not receive direct complaints,
who is IIDA, which regulates all the insurance
companies, tells them everything about
what to do and how to do it, so
if you complain on IDA, it does
not look into it itself  If you have filed a complaint with IADA,
what will IADA do? It will
email the Grievance Cell of that company and they will
forward the complaint. The Grievance Cell of that company
then considers that complaint in a little bit better
way. You can do this.
Now how to file a complaint on IRDA, the
best way is to file a complaint on IADA in two or three
ways, you can call the customer care, you
can email the IADA
and the third best way is that I have
made a separate video and you should
watch the video through Bima Bharosa. There is
a proper video of Bima Bharosa,
I will give the link in the description, go to it and you will see
how you can file a complaint through IADA
and forward your complaint to the company. Then
you will get a reply from the Grievance Cell
because if
you file a complaint on IADA, the company gets a timeline of 15 days, so
their Grievance Cell has to reply within 15 days. It is
possible that if you are directly emailing the
company, the company will not be able to handle that thing.  Pay
attention or not, it has been 15 days, 20 days, one
month, two months, there is no response, you keep re-writing,
sending reminders but the
company is not responding, what can you do, you will not be able to
grab their neck by going there,
so send an email to IID, IID grabs their neck,
then within 15 days you will get the
reply of the complaint, the
company will pass the claim or reject it, there is
more than 99% chance that the complaint
will be rejected again, that is your claim
will be rejected again, the same thing happens through IID also,
if it may be passed in some cases,
mostly your case will be rejected, so
now what is the next process, now the next process
is to go to Oman Insurance, how is a complaint made on Oman, what is
its complete procedure,
letter etc., I have explained everything separately in two-
three videos, so
you will find the videos on my channel, I will
give the link in the description also, you
can easily watch the entire process,
everything is explained in detail, then Om Batman, you have made a
complaint, what is Om Batman  It will take at least five
months, see, this is a government
office, it may take five months, seven months also,
if someone is in a hurry,
I filed a complaint, I get comments from
people that it's been a month, I ca
n't find anything, two months, oh brother, this is a government office,
you will have to wait a bit, if you
can't do it then what will you do, you can't
do anything for the government, so you will have to
prepare for at least four to six months, it is
possible that the process may get done soon, for some
people it gets processed in 15-20 days, it is a
matter of luck, it is a
matter of time, so if you filed a complaint on Om Batman
with proper documentation, I have explained all the documentation,
in the next video, other videos,
after filing a complaint on Om Batman, you are
called for hearing, you
can go for hearing now,
that is the fourth step, this hearing can happen, it can happen
offline, it can happen online also,
see, earlier the hearing had started happening online also,
but what used to happen was that people were
facing problems in their headphones, the computer was not
working, sometimes something  There is a big problem
in handling those people, so
they have mostly stopped online,
now they call you offline only, but they refuse, it will
not be possible online, you will have to come to the
office, so you have to go to Om Butman's office for a
hearing, Om Butman
hears only one hearing, unlike the court, there is
only one
hearing here, in that hearing you will be
passed by Arya, either the claim will be passed, that is what is
called, through Om Butman, or your
claim will be put in review by those companies,
if Om Butman feels that
your points are valid then your claim will be
put in review, in this case, that Butman will
refuse you, it is not right, this claim will
not be passed, whichever Om Butman is your state's Om Butman,
you will get the complete list of Om Butman
from the website, I have
explained all those things, you can see in the video,
now if in this case Om Butman did not pass, if it got
rejected from there also, then now the last option
you have is Consumer Code, now Consumer Code  Let me
tell you what is the process for proceedings. Look,
if you want to file a complaint in the Consumer Court, if you want to
file a complaint through the Consumer Court, then
you do not have to go directly to the Consumer
Court.
Whichever is the nearest
District Court to you, or if you
know any
lawyer or advocate in your vicinity, you can ask him. Well, let me
tell you, if
you go to the District Court, there are a lot of
lawyers there. If you tell anyone that you want to
file a consumer complaint, I want to go to the
Consumer Court, then they
prepare a legal notice for 15 days and give it to you.
Now, I will tell you how much it costs and how it is prepared.
Generally, when you
go to the District Court, you
know the rates of all the lawyers, they vary.
Someone will say 3000, 4000, 5000, 10000,
they will say anything, but I am telling you, I am
telling you the fact, if you go there, I will
give you 00 rupees.  It will be done, you will have to
struggle a bit, you will have to search a bit, it will take
hard work, your work will be done even for Rs. 00,
I am telling you, it will be done, there are
many lawyers, poor people, there is no
work in the market these days, they too are
wandering around, they are not able to get work, so even for Rs.
00 someone will be ready to do it for you
and where someone says Rs. 500,
agree immediately and get your work done,
send a legal notice, after the legal notice, then you are
called for hearing
in the consumer court, now what happens in many cases is that
after receiving this 15 day notice, the company agrees to the settlement,
you get a call from the company that
you take this much, take that much, then
you will have to understand each other, for how much do you
settle, do you want the entire claim, half of it, whatever it is, it is
up to you, if you say
no, we want to fight further, whatever it is,
then you will have to follow the proper consumer code process,
which you will have to do, then the same
date after date, here also it goes on for six
months, four months, one year  It may take
more than that, then it may take
time, you will have to deal with that thing
and there will be expenses too. Now if you hire a lawyer
then you will have to incur expenses as well.
Otherwise, if you want, you can fight your case yourself. There are
some provisions in the consumer court. If
you do some internet search etc. and
read a little, then you
can fight your case yourself. It is not necessary that you
need a lawyer. Now, look at what happens in the consumer court,
mostly we have read in the news,
whatever we have heard from our side, in
more than 99% of the cases, the consumer court gives the
decision in favor of the consumer
because they are pro-consumer
because they always support the smaller party,
which because the companies are big parties, it does
not matter to them. In all these things, the
court supports the small people. Therefore, your chances are also higher in the consumer court. There is a
claim fight and
hard work, then your chances of getting the claim are
also higher. You also get compensation and
interest.  Look,
if your case is going to the Ombudsman and the case is being passed by Ombudsman, then
you will not get any interest, you will
not get any compensation, but
you only get the claim amount, whichever
company agrees to give, but
in the consumer court,
you can file for interest compensation, everything, all that is
given to you after
winning the case from the consumer court, okay, so I hope you have
understood this video, this is the
whole process, apart from this, if you have any
question, whatever it is, then you can
mention it in the comment box, for other videos, please
subscribe to the channel,
more such good videos will keep coming.